let  bio = [
    {
      question:`Which of the following characterizes a mature plant cell?`,
      options:[`The nucleus is push to the center of the cell`,
      `The cell wall is made up of cellulose`,
      `The nucleus is small and irregular in shape`,
      `The cytoplasm fills up the entire cell`],
      answer: `The cell wall is made up of cellulose`,
    },
    {
      question:`Which of the following is not a function of the nucleus of a
      cell?`,
      options:[`It translate genetic information for the manufacture of protein`,
      `It stores hereditary information`,
      `It is a reservoir of energy for the cell`,
      `It controls the life processes of the cell`],
      answer: `It is a reservoir of energy for the cell`,
    },
    {
      question:`The dominant phase in the life cycle of a fern is the ?`,
      options:[`Prothallus`,`Sporophyte`,`Antheridium`,`gametophyte`],
      answer:`Sporophyte`,
    },
    {
      question:`Circulation of blood to all parts of the body except the lungs
      is through  `,
      options:["The pulmonary artery",
      `The systemic circulation`,
      `The lymphatic system`,
      `The pulmonary circulation`],
      answer: `The systemic circulation`
    },
    {
      question:`The outer layer of the kidney where the Bowman's capsules are
      found is called?`,
      options:["Cortex","Pelvis","Medulla","Pyramid"],
      answer:`Cortex`,
    },
    {
      question:`Which of the following stimuli is likely to elicit a nastic
      response from an organism? `,
      options:["Touch","Light intensity","Chemical substances","Gravity"],
      answer:"Chemical substances",
    },
    {
      question:`In the male reproductive system of a mammal, sperm is stored in
      the ?`,
      options:["Vas deferens","Urethra","Epididymis",'Seminiferous tubules'],
      answer: "Epididymis",
    },
    {
     question:`The barrier between the maternal and foetal blood is the ?`,
     options:["Placenta","Liver","Umbilical chord",'Uterine wall'],
     answer: "Placenta",
    },
    {
      question:`The two halves of the pelvic girdle are joined together at the ?`,
      options:["Pubic symphysis","Ilium","Pubis","Obturator foramen"],
      answer:`Pubic symphysis`,
    },
    {
      question:`The hormone which regulates the amount of glucose in blood is
      called?`,
      options:["Adrenalin","Auxin","Insulin","Thyroxine"],
      answer:"Insulin",
    },
    {
      question:`Deamination occurs in the?`,
      options:["Kidney","Liver","Pancreas", "Spleen"],
      answer: 'Liver',
    },
    {
      question:`Epiphytes growing on the branches of trees provide an example of
      the relationship known as? `,
      options:["Parasitism","Commensalism","Saprophytism",'Holophytism'],
      answer:"Commensalism",
    },
    {
      question:`The function of ribosome in cells is?`,
      options:["Protein synthesis",`Starch synthesis`,`Transport of material`,
      `Lipid storage`],
      answer: "Protein synthesis" 
    },
    {
      question:`What is the term  used to describe biotic and abiotic factors in
      the environment of an organism`,
      options:['Habitat',"Biome","Ecosystem","Niche"],
      answer: 'Ecosystem',
    },
    {
      question:`Which of the following instrument is not used in measuring
      abiotic factors in any habitat? `,
      options:["Microscope","Wind vane","Thermometer","Hygrometer"],
      answer:"Microscope",
    },
    {
      question:`The smallest organism which shares the characteristic of both
      living and non-living matter are ?`,
      options:["Bacteria","Viruses","Fungi","Protozoa"],
      answer:"Viruses",
    },
    {
      question:`The process by which a red blood cell placed in distilled water
      absorbs water until it burst and release it's content into the
      surrounding is known as?`,
      options:["Plasmolysis","Osmosis","Turgidity","Haemolysis"],
      answer:"Haemolysis"
    },
    {
      question:`Which of the following waste products in plants is excreted
      through the stomata and lenticles?`,
      options:["Carbon dioxide","Alkaloids","Tannins","Anthocyanins"],
      answer:"Carbon dioxide",
    },
    {
      question:`The excretary structure in Earthworm is called?`,
      options:["Malphighian tubule","Flame cell","Nephridium","Kidney"],
      answer:"Nephridium",
    },
    {
      question:`The ability of the eyes to focus on both near and distance objects is called?`,
      options:["Image formation","Refraction","Hypermetropia","Accommodation"],
      answer:"Accommodation",
    },
    {
      question:`The curvature movement of plants in response to the stimulus of
      water is called?`,
      options:['Hydrotropism',"Geotropism","Phototropism","Thigmotropism"],
      answer: "Hydrotropism",
    },
    {
      question:`The organism that has a hydrostatic skeleton is ?`,
      options:["Tilapia","Hydra","Mosquito larva","Earthworm"],
      answer:"Earthworm",
    },
    {
      question:`The structure that is most commonly identified in all living
      cells under the light microscope is the?`,
      options:["Mitochondrion","Chloroplast",'Nucleus',"Ribosome"],
      answer:"Nucleus",
    },
    {
      question:`Which of the following is an organ?`,
      options:[`Guard cell`,`Liver`,`Xylem bundle`,`Blood`],
      answer:"Liver",
    },
    {
      question:`In the woody stems, gaseous exchange takes place through the?`,
      options:["Micropyles","Stomata","Lenticels","Vessels"],
      answer:"Lenticels",
    },
    {
      question:`The tissue for transporting substances manufactured in the leaves
      to other part of the plant is called?`,
      options:["Xylem","Companion cells","Sieve tubes","Cambium"],
      answer:"Xylem",
    },
    {
      question:`Yellowing of leaves is an indicator that the soil lacks?`,
      options:[`Iron, Magnesium, Calcium`,
      `Nitrogen, Sulphur, Potassium`,
      `Sulphur, Phosphorus Iron`,
      `Magnesium, Nitrogen, Iron`],
      answer:"Magnesium, Nitrogen, Iron",
    },
    {
      question:`The lymphatic system of mammals
      rejoins the blood circulatory system at the ? `,
      options:["Hepatic vein","Subclavian vein","Renal vein",
      "Common iliac vein"],
      answer:"Subclavian vein",
    },
    {
      question:`Bacteria multiply rapidly by means of?`,
      options:["Budding","Binary fission","Fragmentation","Spore formation"],
      answer:"Binary fission"
    },
    {
      question:`Which of the following characterizes the white mangrove?`,
      options:["Prop roots","Buttress root","Breathing roots","Stilt roots"],
      answer:"Breathing roots",
    },
    {
    	question: `Which of the following is a functional group that is part of the building block of proteins?`,
    	options: ["phosphate","adenine","amino","ribose"],
    	answer: "amino",
    },
    {
    	question:`Which of the following is a feature common to all three components of the cytoskeleton?`,
    	options:[`They all serve to scaffold the organelles within the cell`,
    	`They all are characterised by roughly the same diameter`,
    	`They are all polymers of protein subunits`,
    	`They all help the cell resist compression and tension`],
    	answer:`They are all polymers of protein subunits`,
    },
    {
    	question: `Which of the following structures could be found within nucleolus?`,
    	options: ["chromatin","histones","ribosomes","nuclesomes"],
    	answer: `chromatin`,
    },
	{
		question:`Which of the following is an example of a unicellular organism?`,
		options:["Mushroom","Amoeba","Hydra","Flatworm"],
		answer:"Amoeba",
	},
	{
		question:`Which of the following is not a tissue found in the human body?`,
		options:["Muscle tissue","Connective tissue","Nerve tissue","Digestive tissue"],
		answer:"Digestive tissue",
	},
	{
		question:`What is the function of the mitochondria?`,
		options:["Photosynthesis","Respiration","Protein synthesis","Digestion"],
		answer:"Respiration",
	},
	{
		question:`What is the function of ribosome?`,
		options:["DNA replication","Protein synthesis","Cell division","ATP production"],
		answer:"Protein Synthesis",
	},








    ];
    console.log(`bio=${bio.length}`)
bio.sort((a,b)=>Math.random() - 0.5);
    for(let item of bio){
      if(!(item.options.includes("All of the above") ||
      item.options.includes("None of the above")))item.options.sort((a,b)=>Math.random()-0.5);
    };
export default bio;
